Guide to the Richard J. Shavelson Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Richard J. Shavelson papers
1970-2010 (inclusive), 1995-2010 (bulk)
1995-2010
SC1067
Shavelson, Richard J.
17 Linear feet (12 boxes)
.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
Richard J. Shavelson is Margaret Jacks Professor of Education and Professor of Psychology (by courtesy) at Stanford University. He holds degrees from the University of Oregon (B.A., Psychology), San Jose State College (M.A., Psychology), and Stanford (Ph.D., Educational Psychology). Before joining Stanford's faculty, he taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and the University of California, Santa Barbara. From 1987-1993 he was Dean of the Graduate School of Education at Santa Barbara.
At Stanford, he served as I James Quillan Dean of the School of Education and as affiliated faculty at the Woods Institute for the Environment. His research and teaching interests include research design, research methods, and assessment for education.
Scope and Contents
.
Access Terms
Cronbach, Lee J., (Lee Joseph), 1916-2001.; Gage, N. L., (Nathaniel Lees), 1917-2008; National Assessment of Educational Progress (Project).; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education.; University of California, Los Angeles.. Center for Research on Evaluation, Standards, and Student Testing.; Education--Research--Methodology.; Education--Standards; Education--Statistical methods; Education--Study and teaching (Graduate); Educational psychology.; Educational tests and measurements; Mathematics--Study and teaching.; Science--Study and teaching.; Stanford University--Faculty.
Collection Contents
- Teaching, Series 1
  - Education 210D (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Education 210D, Assignments #2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Education 211B, G theory, Lecture Notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Education 211B, Notes (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Education 214A (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Education 214A, 1988 Fall (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Education 214A, Midterm, 1988 Fall (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Education 214A, 1990 Fall (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Education 214A, Materials -- Syllabi (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Education 214A, Final Exam (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Education 214A, Advanced Educational Statistics, 1991 Spring (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Education 214A, Naturalistic Research Handout (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Education 214A, Research Methods in ESL, Model Research Paper (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Education 214B, 1991 Winter (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Education 214B, Course Materials (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Education 214B, Yukari (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Education 214B-C (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Education 214C, Abdul Rahman Othman (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Education 215, Handouts (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Education 215A-B, Psychometrics (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Education 215, Psychometrics, Syllabus (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Education 215A, 2989 Fall (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Education 215A-B, Psychometrics, Readings, 1991 Fall - 1992 Winter (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Education 215A-B, IRT Partial Credit Models, 1991 Fall - 1992 Winter (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Transparencies (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Education 215B, Handouts, 1990 Winter (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Education 215A-B, 1989 Fall (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Education 215B, Psychometrics, 1990 Winter (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Education 215A, Psychometrics, 1991 Fall (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Education 215B, 1992 Winter (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Education 215A, Final Exam, 1992 Winter (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Education 216A, lectures (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Education 216A (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Education 210D (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Education 216/210D lecture notes (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Education 221, 1978 spring (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Education 224, Research Methods Lab (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Education 224, Ed Psych Practicum, 1991 fall (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Education 224, 1993 winter-spring (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Education 224, 1993 winter (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Education 232C, curriculum evaluation (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Education 250B, CTE Seminar (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Education 250B, 1998 spring (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Education 250B, 2002 spring (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Education 250B, 2003 spring (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Education 250B, Analysis of Variance, 2004 spring (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Education 250B, Statistics, 1997 spring (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Education 250B, concept maps (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Education 250B, implicit memory experiment (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Education 250B, 2005 spring (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Education 251B, ANOVA, 2007 spring (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Education 251B, Analysis of Variance, 2009 spring (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Education 254: Issues in the Design of Education Research, 2002 winter (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Stat seminar: MRA, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Education 311X (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Education 311X: First Year Doctoral Student Seminar (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Education 267B, Science C and I, STEP (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Education 266X (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Education 266, Fetterman and Kupermuntz (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Action Research, M. Puccio (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Data analysis seminar, 2000 spring (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Education 349Y: Assessment and Accounting in Higher Education, Oxford, 2002 fall (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Education 353C: Problems in Measurement: Generalizability Theory (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Education 353: G Theory (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Education 249X: Assessment and Accountability in Higher Education, 2010 spring (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Education 434: Introduction to Research in CTE (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Education 444X (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Education 257C / Soc 257: Casual Inference in Quantitative Educational and Social Science Research (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Education 349X: Assessment and Accountability in Higher Education, 2005 fall (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Education 215B: Psychometrics, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Education 267B: Curriculum and Instruction in Science, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Education 266X: Social Science Research Methods in Education, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Education 250B #1, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Education 250B #3, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Education 250B, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Education 334X, Technology-based Student Assessment, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Education 334X, Technology-based Student Assessment, course reader, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Education 250B #1, 2002 spring (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Education 250B #2 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Education 254: Design of Educational Research, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Education 349X: Assessment and Accountability in Higher Education, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Education 255 / Psychology 133, Human Abilities, course reader, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Education 160: Introduction to Statistical Methods in Education, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Education 255Y / Psychology 133Y / Human Biology 158, 2004 winter (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Education 255Y / Psychology 133Y / Human Biology 158, course reader, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Education 359A; Research in Science and Mathematics Education, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 10-15)
  - Education 160: Statistical Methods in Education, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Education 255 / Psychology 133 / HumBio 158: Human Abilities, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Education 255 / Psychology 133 / HumBio 158: Human Abilities, course reader, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Education 359A: Research in Science and Math Education, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Education 359C: Generalizability Theory, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - G Studies (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Education 210B, 1972-1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Test Theory: The Consistency and Interpretability of Education," draft, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Education 210B, 1975-1984 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Education 210B, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Education 211B: Test Theory, 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Education 210C, 1978-1986 (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
  - Education 210/214A, 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - Education 216A: Multivariate Statistics, 1986-1993 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - Education 215A: Psychometrics, 1989-1991 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Education 215A: Psychometrics, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
  - Education 215B: Psychometrics, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Education 255: Human Abilities, 2002 fall (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Education 255 / Psychology 133: Human Abilities, 2003 winter (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Education 255 / Psychology 133: Human Abilities, 2004 winter (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Education 255 / Psychology 133 / HumBio 158: Human Abilities, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Education 369 / Psychology 133: Human Cognitive Abilities, 2009 winter (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Education 359A: Science and Math Assessment and Evaluation (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Education 255 / Psychology 133: Human Abilities, course reader, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 7-9)
  - Education 160: Introduction to Statistical Methods in Education (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Education 160: Introduction to Statistical Methods, 2005 fall (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Education 160: Introduction to Statistical Methods, 2006 fall (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Closing the Inequality Gap: ASSU Student Initiated Course (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Education 210A, midterm, 1986 fall (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Education 210B, 1984 winter (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Education 210C, 1983 spring (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Education 210C, 1987 winter (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Multiple Comparisons (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Education 210C, class notes (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Education 210C: one way ANOVA and comps (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Education 210C: Latin square designs (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Education 210C: hierarchical designs (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Education 210C: confounded blocks design (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Education 210C: split plot design (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Education 210C: administrative (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Education 210C: randomized block design (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Education 210C: completely random factorial design (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Education 210C: analysis of covariance (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Education 216A, 1993 fall (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Education 216A, handouts, 1993 fall (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Education 217X, Philosophical and Methodological Issues in Education Research (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - STEP faculty meeting, 1998 Oct 27 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Sweden, U. Goteborg, 1998 Aug (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lisrel workshop, Byrne (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Methodology talk: Qt and Ql in Policy Research (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - G Theory -- Erlich (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Education 311x, 1999 fall (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Education 311x, 2000 winter (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Education 311x, 2000 spring (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Test item bias (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Education 217X, Philosophical and Methodological Issues in Education Research, Phillips and Shavelson, 2006 winter (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Education 311, Seminar for First Year Doctoral Students, course readers, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Education 311, Seminar for First Year Doctoral Students, course readers, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Projects
  - Foundational Approaches in Science Teaching, University of Hawaii documents, 2001 and undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Teachers' Guide to the Study of the Next Generation of FAST, 2003 Jul (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - FAST Teacher's Guide to the Reflective Lessons, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - FAST Curriculum and Assessment Suite, Stanford Educational Assessment Laboratory, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 19-20)
  - Embedding Assessment in the FAST Curriculum: On Beginning the Romance among Curriculum, Training, and Assessment (National Science Foundation), 2001 (Box 7, Folder 21-23)
  - National Science Foundation grant, Embedding Assessment in the FAST Curriculum #2, human subject approvals (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - National Science Foundation, "Romance" grant, reflective lesson suites (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - National Science Foundation, "Romance" #2, 2003-2005 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - National Science Foundation, "Romance" pilot study, assessment suite, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Romance trial #1, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Romance trial #2, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Romance project pilot study (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Romance/CRESST reading (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - CRESST [National Center for Research on Evaluation, Standards, and Student Testing], 1995-1999 (Box 8, Folder 9-11)
  - CRESST, Project 3.1, 1998-1999 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - CRESST reports, 1996-2000 (Box 8, Folder 13-17)
  - CRESST, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - NSF / CRESST / Romance / ADT / Embedded Access and End Unit, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Center for Assessment and Evaluation of Student Learning (CAESAL), 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Center for Assessment and Evaluation of Student Learning, Framework Retreat, 2003 Jan 5-7 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Center for Assessment and Evaluation of Student Learning, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - APS Assessment History, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - APS sample test questions, 1928-2001 (Box 9, Folder 5-9)
  - NAEP [National Assessment of Educational Progress] Framework Project, 2005-2006 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - NAEP Framework, draft, 2005 Jul 29 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - 2009 NAEP Science Framework, summary of feedback on drafts, circa 2005-2006 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - NAEP Science Framework, cognitive dimenstions (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - NAEP Planning Committee meeting, 2004 Dec 9-10 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - NAEP Planning Committee meeting, 2005 Mar 10-11 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - NAEP Planning Committee meeting, 2005 May 26-27 (Box 9, Folder 16-17)
  - NAEP Planning Committee meeting, 2005 Jun 27-28 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - NAEP Specifications Subcommittee meeting, 2006 Jan 5-6 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - NAEP item and test specifications document, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - NAEP test specification meeting, 2005 Jan 5-6 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - NAEP meeting #2 (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - Development of Alternative Assessments in Science, workshop, 1999 Jan (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - The National Academies Center for Education, Committee on Scientific Principles in Education Research, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - The National Academies Center for Education, Committee on Scientific Principles in Education Research, workshop, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - NAS/NRC Committee: Scientific Principles in Education Research, workshop (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - University of Michigan affirmative action case, Stanford Institute for Higher Education Research amicus curae brief, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 9-14)
  - National Education Sciences Act of 2002, proposal (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - STEP testing talk (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Washington State science exam (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - On Performance Assessment, syllabus from Sweden, 1998 Aug (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Assessing Knowledge, University of Fribourg, 1997-1998 (Box 10, Folder 19-20)
  - California Learning Assessment System, comments on technical advisory committee, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Cognitive Aging Meeting, Stanford Center on Longevity, 2008 Apr 15 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Stanford Institute for the Environment, Education Committee, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Stanford Institute for the Environment, Education Committee, #2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Computerized Cognitive Training, Pilot Study, Wallenberg Global Learning Network, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Computerized Cognitive Training, Wallenberg Global Learning Network, 2005-2007 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Interdisciplinary Graduate Program in Environment and Resouces, Ph.D. Student Handbook, 2006 Oct (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Lee J. Cronbach alpha project (Box 11, Folder 5-7)
  - Lee J. Cronbach (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Lee J. Cronbach obituaries (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Nathaniel L. Gage memorial resolution (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Dissertation draft, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Dissertation draft with comments from Lee J. Cronbach, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 12-13)
- Restricted Materials
  - Term Papers, Accountability in Higher Education, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Term Papers, Human Abilities, 2002 (Box 12)